Finding Aid for Ruth Braden McNamee Papers 1964-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ruth Braden McNamee Papers 1964-1984
McNamee, Ruth Braden, 1921-
0.5 linear ft.
Mayor of Birmingham, Michigan, 1970-1971, and Republican member of the Michigan House of Representatives, 1974-1984. Biographical material, speeches and articles, subject files relating to her public service activities, and photographs.
88561 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Ruth Braden McNamee (donor no. 7179 ) in April 1985 and July 1986.
The collection is open for research.
Ruth Braden McNamee was born in New York City in 1921. She attended Bucknell University, receiving a bachelor's degree in 1942 in political science and English. In 1946, she married William A. McNamee with whom she has two children.
McNamee served on the Birmingham (Michigan) city commission from 1965-1974. She was also mayor of Birmingham from 1970-1971. In 1974, McNamee was elected to the Michigan House of Representatives as a Republican representing the 64th district in Oakland County. She was re-elected to her seat in 1976, 1978, 1980, and 1982 but chose not to run in 1984. In addition, she has held positions as Oakland County supervisor (1968), member of S.E.M.C.O.G. (1969-1974), trustee of the Michigan Municipal League, and trustee of Bucknell University (1982-1987).
Highlights of her career include passage of Birmingham's fair housing ordinance, controlling the civil disturbance of August 1970, drafting a state law regulating transactions in precious metals, and casting the deciding vote in 1984 in the Michigan House against a US constitutional convention on the balanced budget issue.
The papers of Ruth Braden McNamee cover her career in politics from 1964 to 1984 and include four inches of material. Most of the material is from her service as mayor of Birmingham (1970-1971) and as a state representative from Oakland County (1974-1984). The papers have been divided into four series: Biographical/Personal, Speeches and articles, Birmingham city government, and Michigan house of representatives. There are also several photographs which remain with the papers in a separate folder at the end of the collection.
Most of the collection is made up of legislative newsletters, press releases, and speeches given by McNamee. In the last two series, there are also interesting files on: Birmingham's fair housing ordinance, the first passed by referendum in a white community in the country; the 1970 Birmingham-Detroit mayoral exchange between McNamee and Roman Gribbs; the August 1970 riot in Birmingham which led McNamee to declare a state of emergency, impose a dusk to dawn curfew, prohibit public gatherings, and contemplate requesting National Guard forces; the Precious Metals Recovery Act; her 1984 vote against a US constitutional convention; and correspondence with the Millikens, mostly Helen, on the Equal Rights Amendment.
Subjects:
Birmingham (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Discrimination in housing--Michigan.; McNamee, Ruth Braden, 1921-; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Women legislators--Michigan.; Women mayors--Michigan--Birmingham.; Mayors--Michigan--Birmingham.; Legislators--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
McNamee, Ruth Braden, 1921-; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Milliken, William G., 1922-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Vita and Overview Articles (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1964-1984 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors (Box 1)
  - Campaign Materials (Box 1)
  - Political scrapbook containing correspondence and clippings, 1965-1985, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Papers largely concerning religious views and politics, 1965-1985 (Box 1)
    (correspondence, articles, etc.)
- Speeches and Articles
  - 1970-1981 (Box 1)
- Birmingham city government
  - Fair Housing Ordinance, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Birmingham-Detroit Mayoral Exchange, May 1970 (Box 1)
  - Civil Disturbance (parks riot), August 1970, clippings and correspondence (Box 1)
- Michigan House of Representatives
  - Legislative Newsletters, 1975-1981 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases, 1975-1984 (Box 1)
  - Precious Metals Recovery Act, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - US Constitutional Convention, 1984, clippings and correspondence (Box 1)
  - Milliken, William and Helen, 1978-1983 (correspondence and 1978 nomination speech) (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Campaign photo and bill signing (with Governor William Milliken) (Box 1)